this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society IEEE software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host brijesh amanat and today
my guest is John smart John is a
business activity practitioner thought
leader and Coach John is the lead author
of The award-winning and best-selling
book sooner safer happier patterns and
anti-patterns for business agility John
previously was Global business agility
lead and partner at Deloitte prior to
this John LED Vaso working globally for
Barclays Bank John has been an agile and
Dean practitioner since the early 90s
John is also the founder of Enterprise
agility leaders Network a member of
programming committee for devops
Enterprise Summit a member of the
business agility Institute advisory
Council a guest speaker at London
Business School and speaks at numerous
conferences every year both me and John
have worked together in our previous
roles and I have also reviewed John's
book
John welcome to software engineering
radio thank you brijesh we will be
talking today about patterns and
anti-patterns for the successful
delivery of software and Enterprises
based on John's book better values
sooner safer happier we have covered
agile in Enterprises previously in
episode 420 Ryan Ripley on making scrum
work episode 401 Jeremy Miller on
waterfall versus agile episode 238 Linda
Rising on the agile brain let's get
started with a session by understanding
the driver SBI in writing the book who
was the target audience for the book and
what motivated you to write the book
John so thank you brijesh the target
audience for the book is leaders at all
levels in all roles
so it's very much aimed at people
working in large organizations looking
to improve their ways of working and not
only people in technology not only
software engineering but also outside of
technology or people with no technology
background
so as much as possible the goal is to
try to use plain English and minimize
the use of language that might be
perceived to be jargon and in terms of
what prompted me to write the book
it's I've had I think speaking of the
devops Enterprise Summit knowing Gene
Kim and then talking to Gene about the
book writing process it was I don't know
it's just like an aspiration I had to
and a bit of an experiment to write a
book and I think being in that devops
Enterprise Summit I.T Revolution
Community there are a number of people
that have written books and Gene running
his own book publishing company so then
I had a conversation with Gene hey what
does it take to write a book and then
next thing you know two and a half years
later there's a book thanks I think it's
pretty clear to me and the audience on
the drivers for writing this book and I
know in your book you talk about better
ways of working in the age of digital
and the focus shifting to outcomes what
do you think has driven this change so
in sooner say for happier we are
absolutely advocating a focus on the
outcomes first and foremost and the
anti-pattern here is where organizations
do an agile transformation where it's
all about the a word it's all about
agile agile is not the goal the goal is
something else the goal is quicker time
to Value quicker time to learning height
more engagement with colleagues higher
levels of Engagement happier customers
so that this is the key my key learning
the lesson I learned the hard way and
the mistake I made when I started out
leading ways of working across a large
Financial Services organization with 80
000 people we were running an agile
transformation we were measuring the
wrong things we were measuring how many
agile teams and so on how many people
have been trained in agile but that's
not the goal the goal isn't to do Agile
hence the language of better value
sooner safer happier which is quality
better is quality value is value which
is unique sooner it's time to Value
safer is agile Not Fragile and happier
is happier customers colleagues citizens
and climate so what really what we are
coaching organizations on advocating for
is to focus on the outcomes and then
there's not one size fits all as to how
you get there because every organization
is unique and that is a message that
seems to be resonating not surprisingly
thank you John and I also know that in
your book you talk about business
agility I wonder if you could explain a
bit about what is business agility and
why it is important so we are lucky
enough to be alive in a once in a
hundred year
pivot in ways of working in how we do
what we do and it might even be more
than once in a hundred year it might
actually be once in 250 years so what is
business agility it is improving ways of
working in order to improve outcomes and
the background to this is repeating
technology-led revolutions and so back
in 1771 we have the first Industrial
Revolution and that was the very first
time that we went from kind of craft
working to division of labor and working
in a factory and it is still the case
today 250 years later that you can trace
the DNA of ways of working in a large
organization which is doing knowledge
work which is unique and unknowable you
can trace the ways of working all the
way back to 1771 and the very first
factories that were in Derbyshire in
northern England and so business agility
is improving ways of working to deliver
better outcomes and it's triggered by
the latest technologically LED
Revolution which is the age of digital
and it's driven by competitive pressure
because no longer can companies take a
long time to have a feedback loop on the
value that they're producing right and
do you think business agility or the
lack of rather more of a problem in
large Enterprises rather than smaller
firms no I don't actually so I think
that I think it's less to do with size
and it's because what I'm quite
interesting what I'm seeing is for both
small and medium companies
it doesn't take long for small and
medium companies to end up with the same
level of cautiously use the word
dysfunction that the same level of
bureaucracy
and dysfunction as a large company and
it doesn't take long for people to start
to introduce more process more gated
controls
and to slow down the flow of value
irrespective of the size and there are
some relatively small companies
I see who are not very Nimble and don't
have a lot of agility so yeah I think
it's kind of a it's a human
characteristic to keep adding more
process and bureaucracy all right so
irrespective of size business agility or
lack of this problem which is across the
forms in the industry right now yes if
the organization doesn't have an
intentional priority and focus on time
to value and time to learning and
minimizing time to learning then yes
that's the case yes you mentioned the
four metrics better for Quality value
which is Unico cares sooner for time to
Market safer for governance and
compliance and happier for morale we
will take into each of these measures
but I just wanted to understand you know
when you look at it holistically is any
one particular measure more important
depending on which stage the company is
at or the project or the program is that
I would say no definitely not what I
would say is that the the five measures
of better value soon a safer happier are
equally important because they are
balancing outcomes so what we've seen is
that organizations that reduce time to
Value but do it badly for example
working people harder rather than
improving the system of work and
removing impediments what happens not
surprisingly is quality goes down and
happiness goes down so they are
balancing measures so if you are
reducing your time to Value you're
delivering value sooner you should see
quality get better and you should see
happiness get better and if you don't
you know that you're not going about it
the right way
so I would say that they are equally
important right with that let's deep
dive into some of the patterns and
antibatterns that you have covered in
the book and you also touched on the
first anti-pattern that you mentioned in
your book which was doing in agile
transformation why is doing an agile or
a lean or a devops transformation and
anti-pattern can you expand on this and
it's a related pattern which is the
focusing on outcomes yeah so like as I
said agile is not the goal lean is not
the goal devops is not the goal it's a
means to an end it isn't the end and so
often what happens when an organization
runs an agile transformation all the
focus is on the wrong thing the focus is
on are we doing agile how many agile
teams do we have how many people have
been through agile training how many
product owners do we have how many teams
are doing stand-ups yeah who's doing
sprints it does not necessarily lead to
better outcomes for example Nokia mobile
Symbian operating system which no longer
exists because they went bust according
to the chairman of Nokia the thing that
killed Symbian was a lack of
psychological safety so bad news was
being buried bad news was not bubbling
up and the Symbian team were scoring you
know 99 on their how agile are we test
on their scrum test so scroll drum
didn't save Symbian and that's because
scrum is not the goal agile's not the
goal it's the outcomes of quality value
time to Value safety and happiness so
that's the anti-pattern of agile
transformation there is a related
anti-pattern which is the word
transformation so a couple of
anti-patterns here one is doing a
capital T transformation a big bang a
big bang transformation is an
anti-pattern because it takes time for
people to unlearn and relearn and so if
an organization does a big bang where
you leave on Friday you're a project
manager you start on Monday you're a
product owner and this is across the
entire organization with tens of
thousands of people there is no way that
people can magically transform over the
weekend so you end up with new labels on
the same old Behavior humans have a
limited velocity to unlearn and relearn
so if you want to go faster we need to
encourage the speed of unlearning to do
that we need to have more psychological
safety so in order to go faster the best
thing to do is to increase the
psychological safety so that's the
anti-pattern around the word
transformation so the pattern is instead
focus on the outcomes I recommend better
value sooner say for happier quality
value time to Value safety and happiness
and think big start small learn fast so
don't do a capital T transformation do a
lowercase T continuously transforming
it's not a project it doesn't have a
start date and an end date it's about
continuous Improvement aligned to the
outcomes you are never done because
human systems entropy human systems go
backwards so it's about continuously
improving with a lowercase t with
empowerment and autonomy excellent you
do touch on quite a few points and
topics that I plan to cover as we go
through this session and I'll pick on a
few right now so you stress a lot on
outcomes how are outcomes different from
outputs so output Works in a factory
type scenario in the age of oil and mass
production the focus is on output and
the definition of productivity is the
number of units of output per unit of
input so an output is a thing it's a
deliverable it's a widget it is maybe a
piece of software it's a system and if
we focus on the output so for example
have you delivered system X have we
delivered feature y those are all
outputs those are not outcomes and so
the common anti-pattern here at
organizations is a Relentless focus on
the output but with hardly any focus at
all on the outcome so the reason for the
output is to achieve a certain outcome
so the outcome might be increased market
share increase Revenue support more
first-time buyers onto the property
ladder it might be increased market
share in Latin America it might be help
people to buy affordable furniture for
their apartment that's the outcome so
then it might be happy peer customers
might be another outcome the output is
how you might achieve the outcome so
this is a big mindset shift this is a
big mindset shift from output to
outcomes and this includes
experimentation and experimentation
mindset because change is unique change
is unknowable there are unknown unknowns
we don't know what we don't know we've
never done it before and the only way to
learn is by doing so we have to run
experiments and we have to minimize time
to learning and feedback so that we can
pivot so that we can have the cheapest
cost of failure is what we're looking
for so this is a big change in mindset
from it's not about milestones in a
project plan that is not the definition
of success the definition of success is
the key results in an okr objectives and
key results have we actually added a
value and are we adding thin slices of
value Right Moving On I want to touch on
psychological safety because in your
book you do mention that this is not
number one factor in building High
performing teams let's start with the
basics what is psychological safety and
why is it so important
psychological safety is the ability to
feel safe to ask questions to challenge
authority to have your voice heard to
express your thoughts without fear of
repercussion
without fear of being shot down
or belittled in any way it's the ability
to have open vulnerable conversations
with respect and it's also about not
having a blame culture so if something
goes wrong it's not because somebody did
something wrong it's because there was
something in the system of work that
enabled this thing to happen so for an
example of this the British Airways are
cleaner ended up you know shutting down
a data center hitting a power switch
which Switched Off a whole bunch of
servers and that meant that there was a
global outage for British Airways of
their I.T systems and you know the the
CEO of iag the parent company blamed the
cleaner blamed the person who flipped
the power switch but no the real thing
at fault there is that it was possible
to flick a switch to power down the data
center so that's the key thing about
psychological safety is it's a
generative culture where people can
challenge authority just one other
example is where the first Captain the
first officer imagine you're flying a
plane you've got the captain and you've
got the first officer so psychological
safety is the ability for the first
officer to challenge the captain and for
the captain to respond productively and
positively to the challenge and there is
at least one air disaster if not more
where there was a lack of psychological
safety between the captain and the first
officer so the first officer saw a
problem but didn't say anything because
they were fearful for being shouted at
and then that led to an accident right
so closely related to being able to
speak up and express your opinions
correct yes
how can leaders create a psychologically
safe workplace and my go-to reference on
this is Amy Edmondson and her book
called The Fearless organization and I'm
going to quote Amy Edmondson on this in
terms of how to do this so step number
one is set the stage step number two is
invite participation step number three
is respond
positively so step number one set the
stage is psychological safety is
important to us it's a behavioral trait
which I as a leader you know I value
this behavioral trait very much I'm very
keen to nurture a culture of
psychological safety what that means is
it's not about blaming people there's a
blame free culture it's about the system
of work and if you have an opinion if
you have a thought you can respectfully
challenge people with emotional
intelligence
and so on so that's setting the stage
indicator that this behavior is desired
number two invite participation so then
if something does go wrong you know
there's often learned helplessness with
people and so just by saying hey
everyone behave in a psychologically
safe manner it's not going to happen
especially if there's been a culture of
fear in the past it takes I've seen this
happen where you know where leaders have
said we want to create it you know we
want there to be a psychologically safe
environment but the people have had so
much fear in the past that there's it
takes you know two or three years before
people start actually feeling safe so
you've got to you know really encourage
people so that's invite participation
let's celebrate intelligent failure have
a town hall like actually celebrate
learning through failure that's number
two number three is respond positively
respond productively so when something
does go wrong role model the behaviors
you know make it all about the system of
work make it all about what could we do
to prevent this from happening before
and it's not about the individual and
also I think when having kind of team
sessions
psychological safety is allowing people
to express their thoughts and just
acknowledging that everyone's
perspective is right you know and not
putting people down or not saying you're
wrong but just honoring other people's
perspectives thanks John I think
psychological safety you have explained
it very well and our listeners will now
know why it's important and what it is
in your book about leadership you also
talk about transformational leadership
what are the attributes of
transformational leadership so the
attributes of transformational
leadership there are four components the
first one is to role model to walk the
talk the origins of the word lead comes
from to guide on a journey
that's where the word comes from to
guide on a journey is so it doesn't mean
hey you go and do that thing and I'm
going to stay here I'm not going to
change so role model Walk The Talk
number two is articulate a Clear Vision
so this is being painting the picture
very clearly of what the goal is what
the vision is what the purpose is and it
should be something that really does
have purpose so that people feel
intrinsically motivated so for example
making the world of work more Humane
that's a great vision with lots of
purpose the third attribute of
transformational leadership is
intellectual stimulation and this is
about challenging the status quo
questioning assumptions experimentation
and requires empowerment requires
autonomy with a very clear goal and then
the fourth one is being a coach so this
is the leader as a coach coaching people
developing people recognizing strengths
in people
and helping people to grow thanks John
you've touched on system entropy and I
think that's something you also going to
get while you describe the anti-pattern
going faster leads to going slower can
you expand first on water system entropy
how is it related to technical
excellence
and then maybe expand on the
anti-pattern itself sure so entropy so
human systems entropy Technical Systems
entropy and what that means is they kind
of go backwards over time kind of get
worse in the case of Technology there's
more technical debt there's more treacle
it takes longer to get stuff done in the
case of human systems there's more
bureaucracy there's more process there's
more approvals there's more committees
and we people we humans you know we like
to keep on adding processes and rather
than taking things away so given that
human systems entropy given that
Technical Systems entropy over time
I.E go slower get more sticky or
trickle-like it is necessary to
continuously improve continuously
improve in terms of culture in terms of
process and in terms of technology so
technical Excellence is very important
here because and this is the problem if
the focus is just on agile and just on
scrum there's nothing there about
technical Excellence unlike extreme
programming where there is a focus on
technical excellence
so it's very very important to have a
focus on technical Excellence
continuously to continuously refactor to
continuously improve and to dedicate
some bandwidth to that continuous
Improvement improving daily work is as
important as daily work and not doing
that you end up with a go slow to go
faster or you will end up going slower
right so the recommendation or the
pattern that you should adopt is go slow
or to go faster correct and it's a bit
tongue-in-cheek what that means is make
sure that it's important to put time
aside all of the time for continuous
Improvement in the case of technology
for refactoring and continuously
improving not only the technology but
also your ways of working as well
right in this context you also talk
about evergreening what is evergreening
and how can teams be intentional in
adopting it yes evergreening means
always staying up to date with the
latest versions of libraries the latest
supported versions of software and never
allowing yourself to get so far behind
that it's almost impossible to catch up
again and again a bit like refactoring
it requires intention it requires being
deliberate it requires bandwidth it
requires time and it requires money to
always stay up to date with the latest
version of software thanks any examples
come to mind where forms have not done
it and what was the consequence yeah so
an anonymous example at one large
organization where historically there
had not been a focus on evergreening the
technology landscape there was a lot of
software which was completely
unsupported and I mean like a lot of
software in some cases kind of mission
critical parts of the organization and
and in some cases that the software that
was being used or the platform or the
language had been out of support for you
know 10 15 years and not only that but
actually was outside of the license and
that was because of a lack of a focus on
the topic and another example is where a
third part you know I'm sure everyone
has seen this in large organizations
where you'll have a big third party
system and that big third party system
doesn't get upgraded over time and it's
so out of date that you have no choice
you now can't upgrade to the latest
version
and so one example at one organization I
worked at in order to plug in some in
the context of financial services to
plug in some pricing modules it was
necessary to use an unsupported out of
date old version of the C plus compiler
because the third party
product was so out of date so it had a
knock-on effect where everything was
kept at an old version and it was
impossible to upgrade it so it forces
you into a corner where the only thing
you can do is slash and burn and rewrite
it will roll out a new system which is
also not a good idea so that's an
example of the implications of not
having an evergreen type Focus just one
thing to add actually it also holds the
business back so the ability to add
business value it takes longer it's
harder and there was a whole load of
stuff that can't be done because of a
lack of being Evergreen right I
completely agree with you and I've seen
quite a few examples in my career as
well whether that's a bit not C plus
plus but VB6 or COBOL and so on but it's
just been a struggle to upgrade and keep
it up to date you've touched on value
and value is usually answering the
question do our solution meet the needs
of our customers in the business
but this is a lagging indicator are
there any reading indicators that help
measure value that's a good question so
what I find works well is using okrs to
measure value and okr objective and key
result or outcome and key result what I
prefer to call them and within the key
results the key results are your
measures of value and what I recommend
is some of your key results are leading
key results they are indicators that
might lead to later value and some of
your key results are lagging key results
which are value so for example you're
lacking key results might be customer
net promoter score has gone up by 10
points and another one might be we've
increased our market share from 55 to 65
so those are two lagging value measures
customer happiness and market share some
of your leading value measures might be
we've had more downloads of the app on
the App Store that itself is not
valuable
however it is a leading indicator
that might lead to the lagging value
another example would be we've gone from
ten thousand to twenty thousand online
applications for a new product using our
app from the app store again the number
of online applications is itself not
valuable but it's probably going to lead
to an increase in market share so that's
an example of leading and lagging value
measures and what you're trying to do
there is you're trying your leading
indicators your leading key results
you're trying to minimize time to
learning and minimizing time to Value
you're trying to get a really fast
feedback loop and this is where kind of
Carpaccio comes in you want really thin
slices of value get it out to Market get
it in the hands of a customer and then
let's see you know do the key results
start moving right makes sense before we
move on to some of the other patterns I
did want to you know just wanted to have
one final question on Tech Excellence
which is what are some good metrics to
measure technical Excellence that's a
good question I would say off the top of
my head for me it all comes back to like
the lagging measures of time to Value so
lead time flow efficiency the amount of
time the work is being worked on versus
the end-to-end lead time quality and by
quality I mean failure demand I don't
mean defects I mean unplanned work which
is failure demand that's another measure
quality and safety so in terms of better
value sooner say for happier the word
safety and safer is in particular to do
with mandated controls like information
security data privacy encrypting data at
move encrypting data at rest two-factor
authentication not making the newspaper
headlines because customer data has been
hacked and leaked onto the internet so
safer is another important measure and
then obviously I think obviously but
this one's usually missed is happier and
that's happier colleagues as much as it
is happier customers and that's
something that's missing from the Dora
metrics you know or from accelerate you
know the word happier is not there
that's the one that's usually missed so
I would say in summary I would say time
to Value lead time and flow efficiency
quality safety and happiness all of
which leads to business value agreed
because the creator of the technical
grab that you've got the slower you're
going to be and the unhappier developers
are going to be because they're going to
spend a lot of time yep working on stock
videos quite old and Legacy and
difficult to work on and yeah and has a
long lead time the flow efficiency is
low and also the quality will be poor as
well in terms of complexity that fits in
your head
you know if it isn't possible to have a
short lead time it's going to end up
being big change and that's complexity
that doesn't fit in your head you're
more likely to have quality problems
agreed so moving on in your book you
write about building the right thing and
in this context you write about
intelligence Pro and intelligent control
which is around building the thing right
let's start off by understanding what is
intelligent flow so intelligent flow
also known as lean portfolio management
and so there are two components to this
the first component is horizontally
having multi-disciplinary teams
long-lived multi-disciplinary teams
aligned to the customer and aligned to
the flow value so for example in
financial services it might be mortgages
it might be current account in
Investment Bank it might be Equity
trading in an energy company it might be
low carbon value stream it might be gas
and it might be electric vehicle
charging so that's the First Dimension
to intelligent flow is long-lived
multi-disciplinary teams with long-lived
products both business products and it
products aligned to the customer so
there are three things you need you need
to have a thing of value for example
electric vehicle charging you need to
have value consumers the customers that
turn up and charge their electric
vehicles and you need to have value
producers the team both software
engineering teams and the hardware teams
and the electrical engineers that create
the electric vehicle charging points so
if you've got those three things
something of value a consumer and a
producer you have a value stream so
that's one dimension and then on top of
that you have then a vertical Dimension
and this is where the okrs come in the
outcomes and key results so on top of
your nested value streams you have your
okrs so now what we have is we have a
multi-disciplinary team aligned to the
customer they're long-lived with a
long-lived product and they have a very
clear goal to achieve which unites the
team across the role-based silos so we
could have electrical engineers we could
have marketing we could have sales we
could have software engineering everyone
has the same goal and the goal is on the
value stream got it so three attributes
value consumer and producer and
long-lived team yep for a long live team
which is multi-disciplinary what's the
career path you know how do you retain
that
so so you know you you might have the
best of intents and if you're leading
such a team and you manage to create it
how do you ensure that you know there's
a retention and what's a career path for
somebody who's within that long live
team yeah that's a great question so
especially in a large organizations
value streams are nested you have a
double click so if we take for example a
bank a bank is a value stream double
click within that you've got Retail Bank
corporate Bank wealth investment Bank
Global markets and so on double click on
the retail bank you've got mortgages
everyday banking maybe pensions I don't
know tax-free savings so likewise in the
Investment Bank you've got Equity
trading debt trading research so
organizations have nested value streams
so therefore there is room for career
progression within the nested value
streams so an individual might be a
product owner at the team level there is
career progression there to become the
product owner at the team of teams level
the next level up and then the next
level up and then the next level up
there is also career progression so in
terms of long-lived teams just to be
really clear what is meant by this is
it's not a case of come together do a
project and disband which is how it used
to be it also means that it doesn't mean
that people are stuck in a team forever
so there still is mobility there still
is the ability to move around but it's
just not all of the time and it's not
based on a project so it could also be
that there's an area that's very small
maybe there's two teams and career
progression could be to go and work on
another value stream which is much
bigger and maybe there's 20 teams so
your sphere of influence and your sphere
of control
has just grown significantly because
it's a bigger area so there is a very
clear career progression and just to
mention one other thing the pattern that
I find to work well is there are three
leadership roles at every level there's
the value outcome lead also known as a
product owner there's the team outcome
lead or the delivery lead also sometimes
known as a scrum master or a scrum of
scrums Master and then the third one is
the technical lead the architecture
outcome lead or the technical lead so
that is you know the It software
engineering plus architecture
lead now those three roles exist at the
team level and they might just be a hat
that people wear it might not be a
full-time role it could just be a hat
and those three roles exist at the team
of teams level and the team of team of
teams and so on and so on and so on so
again there is career progression there
as a value outcome lead as a team lead
or a team of teams lead and that's a
technical lead thank you that was a very
good answer we'll move on to the another
pattern if you could expand or tell me a
bit more about the Milestone driven
predicted Solutions and the pattern yeah
so that anti-pattern is where the
definition of success is hitting a
milestone a predetermined milestone in a
project plan which was put together at
the point of having learned the least it
is traditionally how organizations have
measured success which is a rag status
red Amber green you know is your
milestone in your plan is it red Amber
or green and in particular when there is
a I'm sure we've all seen this where
there is a lack of psychological safety
nobody wants to put red on their rag
status on their Milestone because you
get summoned to the big boss to the
senior leader who if there is a lack of
psychological safety will then give
people a hard time around why are you
late on your Milestone rather than how
can I help you to to achieve this goal
so then obviously what happens is bad
news is buried senior leaders never hear
about anything everything looks like
it's green until there's a massive
failure
with sunk cost fallacy and things fail
to be delivered which is quite often
quite often observed from old ways of
working so that's absolutely an
anti-pattern and organizations are
complex adaptive systems the butterfly
flaps its wings and there's a tornado a
thousand miles away we don't know what
we don't know there are unknown unknowns
we can't possibly predict the future so
therefore a milestone the origins of
which come from the Roman Empire they
weigh two tons they are sunk six feet
into the ground and they are immovable
is a very bad analogy for change for
unknowable change where actually we want
to be adaptive and we want to have
agility right so if I get it what you're
saying is that Milestone driven
predicted solution is an anti-pattern
because it drives their own behavior and
it incentives team members to
hide information so that because Red
State as seen as something which is bad
there's that if there is a lack of
psychological safety there is the added
complication of burying bad news but
even if there isn't that lack of
psychological safety it's still
sub-optimal to view success as a
milestone in a Gantt chart because
typically that Milestone again because
it's a focus on the output not to focus
on the outcome it's a focus on did we
build system X by date y or have we not
and the business case was written 18
months ago no one has ever looked at the
business case since there's no causality
the time from cause and effect is so
long that you can't possibly measure
value because it could be just a change
in the macroeconomic environment so
instead this is the pivot to focusing on
the outcome rather than on the output
right got it building the wrong thing
faster makes you wronger you touched on
Gantt charts you have a strong opinion
on it can you start by explaining to our
listeners what a grandchild is it's
historical
and why you don't favor its use so a
Gantt chart
Henry Gantt worked with Frederick
Winslow Taylor in the early 1900s in the
context of manual labor in factories and
the line in the Gantt chart originally
used to be called the mandates quota and
what it meant was if you've shoveled
enough coal into the boiler you can go
home if you haven't shoveled enough coal
or if you haven't produced enough steel
then keep on working and so it was used
with a mindset of manual laborers are
dumb manual laborers are stupid manual
laborers need to be told what to do and
can't be trusted so that's the general
School of thoughts from taylorism at the
time with time studies rather than time
and motion which came later and so
that's their Origins and Just one
thought which is to quote Eisenhower
planning is indispensable but plans are
useless so the act of planning is a very
good thing and with agile ways of
working you're actually doing more
planning than you are with a waterfall
way of working with a traditional
sequential big batch way of working
because you're planning continuously
you're doing everything continuously so
you can do anything badly so you can use
a Gantt chart well so you know I'm not
completely opposed to a Gantt chart
because a Gantt chart with lines
representing activity can be used in the
right context and it can be used to
visualize the future it can be used well
and it can be used badly
so what I recommend is first and
foremost fixate on the outcome roadmap
not on the output roadmap so and what I
find works well is Imagine like a double
layer roadmap so the top layer of the
roadmap is is your three-year okr your
one year okr and then your quarterly
okrs so where do we want to be by the
end of q1 where do we want to be by the
end of the full year where do we want to
be in three years time and that's all
expressed as outcomes not as Solutions
underneath that when you double click on
your quarterly okr you will have some
monthly epics or experiments or features
and then you'll have some weekly
iterations and some daily stories and
it's okay like below the quarterly okr I
think it's okay to visualize you know
what the roadmap might be for the
product but the important thing is the
output roadmap should be pivoting all
over the place it shouldn't be locked
down there should not be Change Control
the outcome roadmap above isn't going to
change very much where we want to
increase market share we want to
increase profit margin we want to have
happy customers but underneath that
there should be an enormous amount of
agility to run quick experiments we're
going to try this in the product roadmap
we're going to try this we're going to
try this if it works amplify if it
doesn't work dampen pivot so yeah so
that's my thought process on kind of
planning so if I understood that right
what you're saying is that you've got
your three-year roadmap
one year roadmap and then you've
quarterly road map and underneath the
quarterly road map which has got the
outcomes you could use canned shirts
to show how work is progressing to
achieve that outcome so yeah and I
wouldn't get to personally I don't think
it's not about getting too hung up on a
Gantt charts using a Gantt chart or not
using a Gantt chart from a principal
perspective yes first and foremost
fixate on the outcome roadmap not the
output roadmap whether you use a Gantt
chart or not first and foremost focus on
the outcomes and then when you double
click on the outcome underneath the
outcomes you know you will have an
architecture Vision you will have an
architecture roadmap you will have a
product Vision you will have a product
roadmap and we need to have that we need
to visualize the future for this product
but the important Point here whether you
use a Gantt chart or whether you use an
Excel spreadsheet or Google Sheets it
doesn't really matter the most important
principle here is the product roadmap
the output roadmap should be pivoting
all over the place it should be changing
frequently and it should be changing
frequently based on thin slices of value
minimizing time to learning so that we
can pivot so that we can achieve the
outcome so if I give you an example an
outcome might be we want to get to the
town which is over the river and we've
got 20 people to get across the river
and we want them to be dry and happy
dear team you are free to figure out how
to cross the river to get to that town
not telling the team whether to build a
bridge or build a boat or for people to
swim in the past what we would have done
is we would have had a project plan
where we would have said build a bridge
and told the team exactly what to do
with requirements handed down the line
but now team you're free to go figure so
then the team run a cheap experiment one
person tries to swim yeah it's too deep
it's cold we're not going to get 20
people across happy someone else quickly
builds a look at basic canoe they canoe
across uh you know what the water's
flown too quickly there's Rapids didn't
make it across someone else builds a zip
line ah awesome the zipline Works
everyone's dry it's quick so the
solution ends up being the zip line so I
hope that kind of analogy helps bring it
to life where the product roadmap should
be pivoting all over the place to
maximize the outcome no it does it does
Just one thought came over there which
is around incentive model that you will
have so with the incentive model then be
aligned towards after achieving the
outcome or will there be and if the
outcome is said after three years you
know your market share goes up by X
percent after three years how do you
incentivize the team during this period
what model should it be following yeah
that's a great question so incentives
are so important and I think you can
boil down you know ways of working how
we do what we do improving ways of
working you can boil it down to one word
which is incentive and the other side of
incentive is threat and it's very
important to as per your question is to
align incentives if incentives are not
aligned there will be problems so to
answer your question around incentives
this is where okrs I find work really
well when they're done well so the
anti-pattern is to have okrs in a
role-based silo engineering okrs quality
okrs product okrs Marketing okrs sales
okrs that's an anti-pattern the pattern
is to have value stream aligned okrs so
again this could be mortgages it could
be current account it could be low
carbon energy it could be medicine in
healthcare so what happens here is when
you have okrs which are aligned to the
value stream aligned to the flow of
value in your company the things that
you do a value you know it could be
streaming at Disney it helps unite
people across the job roles to a common
goal so now it doesn't matter whether
I'm Marketing sales engineering quality
whatever we're all United we're all
rowing in the same direction and we
succeed or fail and there is no failing
it's just learning we succeed and learn
as a team together and I've seen it lead
to some really good human behavior where
people get behind each other and they
help each other out and it's a truly
multi-disciplinary team not only
multi-disciplinary in it but genuinely
business plus technology plus Ops
multi-disciplinary teams so okrs are a
great way to align incentives all right
and I think it's related to the
antibattern local optimization where you
see only IIT getting optimized or only
one team of the value chain getting
optimized can you tell our listeners a
bit more about local optimization and
also maybe give the example of the team
that reduce the time between pulling
work from the backlog to the end of
development but still the benefits were
not visible to users what went wrong
over there yeah so to quote Ellie Gold
rat author of the goal a system of local
optimums is not an Optimum system and
local optimization means improving in
one role-based Silo only and for example
that could just be improving in software
engineering improving in it and if it's
no longer the weakest link in the
end-to-end chain
there's no point in continuing to
strengthen it if it's no longer the
weakest link the weakest link has now
moved the theory of constraints put all
of your resources behind the biggest
constraint the biggest bottleneck in the
end-to-end flow the bottleneck moves
somewhere else the weakest link moves
somewhere else identify it repeat and
repeat for Infinity so the example here
is where you know you've got the
end-to-end flow of value your biggest
impediments are typically Upstream
typically annual budgeting the kind of
the portfolio management process the
funding process and the biggest
impediment is not software engineering
and yet you know still it's like teams
could spend lots of time and effort in
reducing the lead time and you could
reduce it by 50 percent however it only
has a five percent impact on the actual
end-to-end lead timer value because the
biggest impediment is Upstream yep
agreed and what would be the way to
solve for it what's the corresponding
pattern number one visualize visualize
the system of work end to end so a great
way to do this is value stream mapping
get all of the experts in the physical
room or the virtual room together at the
same time so you've got experts who know
each little bit of their end-to-end
process and actually map it out for the
first time ever usually visualize it
physically or virtually so we can
actually see the end-to-end flow and
then ask people for roughly how much
time is work waiting in between these
stages and roughly how much time are you
spending adding value to the work and
then you know it's quite easy to then
come up with a an approximate measure
for flow efficiency flow efficiency
again being the amount of time that work
is being worked on versus the end-to-end
lead time for most organizations flow
efficiency is 10 or less which means
that work is sitting in a queue waiting
for ninety percent of the time which is
shocking that's incredibly low and most
organizations are unaware of it because
they're not measuring it
so number one visualize and measure make
it visible measure the system of work
and then identify your biggest
impediment to the flow value it's
usually quite obvious and then work out
what in you know you've got an
impediment work out how you can
alleviate that impediment run some
experiments start with the Champions and
then repeat for Infinity 10 is a
shocking number so what you're seeing
basically is local instead of local
optimization you should be optimizing
for the bottlenecks to reduce the flow
and to analytics correct take a look at
the flow end to end yep from concept to
Cache Right Moving on let's touch on
build the thing right which is about
continuous compliance what would be a
multi-disciplinary control team so we
call them a safety team and this is a
pattern that works well which is in your
safety team you've got a
multi-disciplinary effectively A
specialized secondary team so you might
have 10 product teams aligned to a
values stream let's assume it's
mortgages in a retail bank and then
you've got your safety team and then
your safety team you've got information
security data privacy fraud anti-money
laundering compliance maybe Enterprise
architecture anyone who has some
mandatory risk stories that need to be
implemented and those could be external
regulation or it could be internal
standards policies and standards and the
pattern that works here is it's a long
lived team so it's always the same
people the anti-pattern is you know you
go to infosec you speak to infosec you
speak to data privacy it's always
somebody different you never speak to
the same person they don't understand
the customer's context they're not
specialists in mortgages so that's an
anti-patent and that's you know that's
the world that I've experienced in the
past so with these long-lived safety
teams you can have some amazing
Innovation coming from the safety team
who actually deeply understand the
customer and the customers unarticulated
needs and it's not one size fits all
because the safety team once a quarter
there's a formal kind of conversation
with the product teams this is what
we're planning to build in the next
quarter based on our okr and then the
safety team will decide on kind of the
risk appetite on the risk profile and
then it might be a case if we're going
to talk every day we're going to join
your stand up or it might be a case if
it's not risky at all so we don't need
to speak for another quarter and it's
also not one size fits all when it comes
to the risk stories
that are going to be implemented by the
teams so if you're building something
that's risky you're going to have a
whole load of risk stories encrypting
data and so on two-factor authentication
if what you're building is not risky and
it's internal then don't worry you know
you don't need to do all these things
the anti-pattern which is how it used to
be for most companies is one size fits
all everyone has to comply to the same
200 set of controls do you have any
specific examples where things have gone
wrong by not focusing on safety so I
don't because what I have experience of
implementing is we built in the safety
checks
so we could see both left to right and
right to left so left to right is the
path to production programmatically we
could see if someone had not implemented
a mandatory risk story and that was
reported in a report
and right to left is going backwards
along the software development life
cycle we could see if somebody had
pushed a new binary into production and
if we couldn't trace it back to the risk
stories
that also Shone a big red light in a
report which was Then followed up at a
senior level so actually what I've seen
is yeah we managed to get to a point
where there was both speed and control
not just speed out of control or control
with no speed just one other thing to
mention Rajesh is that where I have seen
it cause historically be a problem in
the old way of working is you know we
had a like a agile Lighthouse initiative
and it was meant to be a big Fanfare in
the spotlight and hey look great case
study of agile ways of working and it
was like the day before go live super
agile
and information security came up with
six months of unplanned work and that
was the old way of working and you know
it's like we're going to inspect it at
the end and oh here's a bunch of new
requirements so that was funny because
this was meant to be a showcase for
agile ways of working and you know what
we learned it absolutely was not agile
at the end
and we learned from it right and this
was primarily because the safety team
was not grossly aligned there wasn't a
safety team okay yeah in that particular
example this was before we even created
the concept of a safety team
so that was an example of the old ways
of working where you know we'll inspect
it at the end and oh by the way here's a
bunch of new requirements and it was
probably because it was someone
different every time you speak to
infosec or data privacy right I want to
touch on the measure happier how do you
measure team morale and satisfaction any
suggestions on that yeah so a couple of
ways the first way is usually there is
an existing HR colleague engagement
survey which is running and so they
usually have a colleague engagement
score so it's usually pretty easy
because it already exists and start with
that the other thing that I recommend
doing that we normally do is we also
have our own colleague ways of working
survey and typically will alternate the
external third-party colleague survey
usually being run from HR with the ways
of working colleague survey and the ways
of working colleague survey is the
questions are very specifically worded
to do with ways of working and what I
found to work well is we ask the same
questions every single time it goes out
every six months so it kind of
alternates with the hr1 which is every
six months so effectively every quarter
we have a feedback loop it works really
well to ask the same questions and one
of the questions is a net promoter score
type question so in terms of how we
measure colleague engagement not only is
there the proprietary third-party
engagement calculation there is also our
own net promoter score type question and
every single time we see the Kubler-Ross
curve we see the peak of excitement we
see the trough of disillusionment all
this is hard and then we see people
climbing out of the hole so it's always
up down up is what we see on the net
promoter score and we also also works
really well is to have free text fields
in that survey and what we do is we use
the colleague feedback to then drive the
strategy for the next quarter so yeah we
every time I've done this we've put a
lot of effort into listening to what
colleagues are saying which then
influences the approach right thanks
John in the last section I'd like to
close of the show talking about what's
in the future we have seen software
development methodologies evolved from
waterfall to an iterative model using
agile lean principles and other tools as
software changes with introduction of AI
machine learning and no code how do you
see software development methodologies
evolving so what would be the new new
ways of working
I think it's even more kind of Biz
devops if you like I think there's still
a big what I observe is there's still a
big gap between in quotes the business
and technology there's a lot of room for
improvement in terms of properly
multi-disciplinary teams which are
business and I.T together you know we
can still have reporting lines into
technology we can still have reporting
lines into non-technology that the
difference is that the work is not
flowing through the reporting line the
difference is the reporting line is
there for personal development and
career growth and care for the
individual and work is flowing in the
value Stream So I think to answer your
question brijesh I think it is
increasingly kind of Biz devops which
for me is a bit Back to the Future for
me it's kind of in my personal
experience it's how we used to work in
the early 1990s yeah I think that's it
it's like you know this breaking down
the barriers even for some Silicon
Valley companies even with the notion of
product and Engineering there still ends
up being like a business Silo a product
Silo and then an engineering Silo and
products are just doing what business
analysts used to do in the past which is
talking to the business writing
requirements and handing them to
engineering which is not great so I
think more outcome focused more value
stream alignment biz devops
excellent we covered a lot of ground
here but if there was one thing you
would want our listeners to remember
from the show what would it be and I
already have a very good inkling about
what you want to say uh focus on the
outcomes yeah that's it first and
foremost it's not about agile it's not
about lean it's not about devops those
are tools in the toolbox first and
foremost number one understand what
outcomes you're going after for example
better value soon to say for happier
feel free to use those words and then
measure them and then continuously have
fun continuously improve in line with
those outcomes great was there anything
we missed that you would like to mention
only maybe just to reinforce the
importance of incentive and the
importance of leadership leadership
Behavior Will Make It or Break It it is
Grassroots will hit a grass ceiling
there will be limited success trying to
do this bottom-up only it has to be in
my opinion this has to be top down and
bottom-up and sideways in the middle out
so maybe just to mention that there has
to be an incentive for this to be
successful across an organization
improve this being improving ways of
working improving how you do what you do
there has to be an incentive from the
top table to improve because if there
isn't an incentive from the top table to
improve people won't improve right
people can follow you on Twitter but how
else can people get in touch LinkedIn
yep Twitter LinkedIn and also our
website sooner saferhappier.com
John thank you for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is
brijesh amanath for software engineering
radio thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this in all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under created Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening